<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honest souldier, or, a vindication of the reduced-officers, otherwise called reformadoes; against the blastings of most grosse untruths, wherewith they have been aspersed : or, the honest souldier, that between Jerusalem and Ierico, fell amongst thieves, who robbed him of his arrears, stripped him of his livelihood, and wounded him in his reputation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E441_34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862798</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862798</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161687</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86511)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161687)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 69:E441[34])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honest souldier, or, a vindication of the reduced-officers, otherwise called reformadoes; against the blastings of most grosse untruths, wherewith they have been aspersed : or, the honest souldier, that between Jerusalem and Ierico, fell amongst thieves, who robbed him of his arrears, stripped him of his livelihood, and wounded him in his reputation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 12th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Pay, allowances, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Soldiers --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161687:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Honeſt Souldier, OR, A VINDICATION OF THE Reduced-Officers, otherwiſe called REFORMADOES; AGAINST The blaſtings of moſt groſſe Untruths, wherewith they have been Aſperſed: <hi>OR,</hi> The honeſt Souldier, that between <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Ierico,</hi> fell amongſt Thieves, who robbed him of his <hi>Arrears,</hi> ſtripped him of his live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood, and wounded him in his Reputation.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALM. 44. verſ. 14.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>All this is come upon us, yet have we not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten thee; neither have we dealt falſly in thy Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Verſ. 18.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our heart is not turned back, neither have our ſteps declined from thy way.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Verſ. 26.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſe, for our help and redeeme us for thy mercies ſake.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:161687:2"/>
            <head>The Honeſt Souldier, OR, A <hi>Vindication</hi> of the Reduced Officers, otherwiſe called <hi>Reformadoes,</hi> againſt the blaſtings of moſt groſſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuths, wherewith they have been Aſperſed.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruth is my Witneſſe</hi> (which needs no Screen) a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (both old and true,) If believed, I have my aime, otherwiſe, I have performed my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; let ſuch as ſcruple it ſpeak impartially, and (I am confident) when time and their own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhall ripen the event, haply then, they may (though late) credit him whoſe daily wiſhes are, the God of goodneſſe may ſpeedily aſſiſt his diſtreſſed Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>It hath been obſerved by divers obliged Officers, ſuch as at S. <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> Church <hi>London,</hi> entred into a <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> by Commiſſions from his Excellency the Earl of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> afterwards, and laſtly, by their Solemn <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant;</hi> That although they have cordially acted accordingly (God protecting their endeavors thorough much perill,) yet have they not tranſgreſſed againſt thoſe Engagements (either in their affections or actions) really for the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> or againſt its Enemies. And notwithſtanding the fidelity of ſuch Officers (to ſo ſtrong Engagements,) moſt faithfully and dutifully performed; others have obtruded into, or have conferred on them the moſt eminent Commands of the Kingdome, (who do not only refuſe to joyn in thoſe Engagements, but doe deteſt and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the thing and all that have ſubmitted thereunto;) although it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161687:2"/>
can never appear that thoſe men ſhewed themſelves more faithfull, or deſerved better from the State or people of <hi>England;</hi> but to the contrary, very many amongſt them have diſobliged the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp;c. and never looked an Enemy in the face, in any Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Field (where Field Service was,) being taking into Service ſince the Kingdomes Enemies were quell'd and all danger paſt: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is obſervable, that the condition of ſuch Officers as acted (to the hazard of their lives, and loſſe of their bloud) for the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> are worſe and in leſſe eſteem, then theirs that acted againſt them; <hi>(O moſt unnaturall times!)</hi> It is undeniable, that the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Intreſt became dubious, and few had engaged for them, had not the Champion of <hi>Englands</hi> Liberties (the Earle of <hi>Eſſex)</hi> undertaken it; A man of unparralled worth, Galentry, Noble birth, fixed principles, and known experience in Marſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires; whoſe perſon only and alone formed an Army, for their (and the Kingdomes) Service; when neither the Power, Declarations, or Remonſtrances of <hi>Parliament,</hi> (in all viſible appearence) could effect it: But how that matchleſſe man (and ſuch gallant ſpirits as as did engage with him) have been gratified, let the covert and hidden thoughts of thoſe that then voted to live and die with him ſpeake, (as in the preſence of the all-ſeeing God) to which I ſhall ſubmit.</p>
            <p>And although matter of much diſcouragement might alſo have been obſerved (in the Occurents of ſuch times) after that excellent man (and the faithfull-men that ſerved the <hi>Parliament</hi> under him,) had with indefatigable paines raiſed and marched with a formidable Army, to ballence their numerous and potent Adverſaries, and had conſtrained them to acknowledge the <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and encouraged their Maſters (the State of <hi>England)</hi> to own that name, untill his Excellency and they had peaceably laid down their Commiſſions, and ſurrendred their Power into the hands that gave it; It, yet being from my purpoſe and a task to hard for me, I wave it: Only that this may redound to his perpetuall and never dying honour (upon whom every dayes additionall experience multiplies the dear affection of his perplexed Countrey,) that having in ſundry great Battels faithfully performed his Truſt, fortunately Conquered their Enemies, and triumphed in the love and hearty affections of all; this Champion of his Countrey ſurrendered his Charge into their hands that gave it, with as much content and quiet, as he had
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161687:3"/>
with magnanimity and courage at firſt undertaken it; although had he diſputed the thing, rubbed up paſt injuries, or demurred untill repairation or ſatisfaction had for himſelfe and others, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and juſt Demands were alſo great, and might more juſtly have challenged that, then ſome have ſince done; certainly, he could never have wanted for power, credit, or greatneſſe to ſupport his under-takings therein, and Vindicated himſelfe and them: But he owned not ſo vile and low a thought, ſelfe reſpects, or other ends then what did wholly tend to his firſt undertaken Intereſt, either to enthrone himſelfe, or purchaſe other being, then what he was born unto, the heir which he aimed to enrich, was the Kingdom and People of <hi>England</hi> only; for whoſe weale he contended, and with that contentedly laid down and died.</p>
            <p>And herein as I intended not a ſcrutiny of his Excellencies parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſufferings, ſo neither have I purpoſed to numerate or ſum up theirs ſubordinate to him, although their diſcontents were infinite, (to their perpetuall diſhonour be it ſpoken, that have ungratefully reaped the haverſt of their ſo perillous, pious, and faithfull endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours;) but where Religion and our duty to God comes into neglect and deriſion, the pious Profeſſours thereof ſleighted, ſcorned and abaſed, our great and admirable deliverances ungratefully recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and in ſtead of Reformation (according to Proteſtations and Covenants promiſed,) a licencious Toleration of Sects, Schiſmes, Heriſies and prophaneſſe; O where the ſacred Ordinances of God have been ſacrilegiouſly trampled upon! what can men (although never ſo well deſerving) expect.</p>
            <p>But hence to my further purpoſe (that is to ſay) how and in what manner the Services and expectations of the Kingdom, became fruitleſſe under the hands of thoſe men commonly called <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does,</hi> is that intended here:</p>
            <p>This afterwards, there aroſe another <hi>Pharo</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> that knew not <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> whoſe Tax-Maſters became cruell &amp;c. Thoſe impoſe impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities, Bricks are expected without Straw; new Lords new Laws, new Mouldings for new Deſigns.</p>
            <p>Now Committees (a new and Arbitrary device) have the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſole Power, commonly choſen in every County of the <note n="*" place="margin">No gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp;c. for both the Kingdom and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers have found ſome noble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Gentlemen amongſt thoſe, as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees of <hi>Hampſhire, Wosterſhire, Shropſhire, Buckingham,</hi> and ſome few beſides that were civill to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and paid the Soldiers.</note> loweſt and meaneſt men (as moſt proper for the purpoſe intended) neither ſhuting with civility &amp;c. or any property becomming ſo honourable a charge, theſe have the Kingdomes ſole Power in laying Aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161687:3"/>
for Contribution, Exciſe, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> part, Delinquents Fines, Compoſitions, and Sequeſtrations; by vertue whereof, as if it had been unanimouſly agreed upon where ever they came, they make ſhort and clear work of the Kingdomes Treaſures, which they hoard up and bank improperly, and the better to ſhelter their cloſe and fraudelent purpoſes herein; the Commanders and Officers Millitary (for whoſe ſupport and entertainment primarily ſuch aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were intended,) are vilified, aſperſed, neglected, thwarted, and diſcouraged; their wages, pay, and ſubſiſtance detained from them, and in a very large meaſure converted to the unſatiable uſe of thoſe Vermine; after their ſupporters, &amp;c. (men generally known) of a ſtraine above thoſe men, and two ſtraines in Covetouſneſſe before them (under whoſe ſcreen thoſe Caterpillers are propt up) had been gratified with the more ſolid weighty part; a practice ſo fully known to the Kingdom, eſpecially, the Counties where theſe men are; and to the <hi>Searchers</hi> of <hi>Graves-end, Dover,</hi> and other Ports of this Kingdome, that I ſhall not need expreſſe here more of it.</p>
            <p>And wherein the Souldiers (for better ſatisfaction) have beene neceſſitated to enter into a ſcrutiny or cloſer diſcovery of ſuch practices; their perſons have been calumniated, detracted, affronted, ſcandalized, diſcouraged, and ſo much made unſerviceable; that the time which they ſhould have better beſtowed in ſervice againſt the Enemies to manage their weighty employments in; they muſt be faine to convert into Solicitations, aſſume the garbe of an <hi>Agitator,</hi> or humble Orator at a Committee-mans Lodging; their Clark or Door-keepers Chamber, trace <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> or by favour crowd into the Loby and there cringe, flatter &amp; faune to the Members for a nod (which hapily may be obtained by the favour of their Servant, Footman &amp;c. a favour beyond their merits or former Service,) a garbe moſt improper and unbeſeeming Souldiers, men of Honour and Gallantry, that would in the face of an Enemy rather breathe their laſt, then daign ſo low and ignoble an employment, chiefly from thoſe men for whom their bloud and lives was not thought deare to purchaſe peace; (but what will not neceſſity force men unto, eſpecially, from ſeeming friends) whoſe civility oblige very much, eſpeciall when ſtrengthened with a conſcientious Cauſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared by <hi>Protestations, Covenants,</hi> and a faithfull winning Generall; wherefore that no juſt ſtaine might ſtick upon their Honours, or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161687:4"/>
blemiſh their Integrity, in diſchage of their duty to God, and their truſt to man, the neceſſities of effecting both being ſo prevalent, <hi>viz.</hi> Recruts of men, money, horſes, arms, ammunition &amp;c. without which undoubtedly the Kingdomes Expectations was not to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, or the Souldiers wiſhed for Victory compleated? and is there any honeſt minded man, but would rather undergoe any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, to ſupport and carry on a concernment ſo high and pious, then deſert it thus for a puntilio of honour, although indeed the poſture be beneath a Souldier, and although alſo the cauſes of their atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance ought to have been provided to their hands (by thoſe men unto whom they became Petitioners;) Nevertheleſſe ſuch was the gallantry, fidelity, and piety of moſt Commanders, Officers and Souldiers, (diſdaining thoſe diſcouragements and infinite more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides) they reſolve rather to ſubmit, caſt themſelves upon the worſt of miſeries and try all concluſions, then deſert their <hi>Covenant</hi> or quit their Truſt.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, here reſteth not the violent and piercing malice of thoſe beginnings, but daily became more heightned upon them, as well to the encreaſe of their diſcontents, as to the ripening of ſome hidden myſtery, then enforcing admiration (but at this day unvailed, and with coulours diſplayed open,) which then cauſed their more narrow and particular ſcrutiny, where in it is diſcovered, that the longer they ſtruggle or ſtrive to ſteare faſt unto their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, the more they are enſnared, untill the ends are obtained, which is either to wreſt their Commands out of their hands, or become dejected Slaves, and hold by villinage from reall Villains their dunghill Committee Lords.</p>
            <p>And when it ſucceeds not effectuall to their expectations thus, ſecondary attempts are endeavoured, either maliciouſly objecting (or putting into the mouthes of their impudent and brazen fore-headed crue of Varlets <note n="a" place="margin">Tub-Preachers Male and Female.</note> to object,) that ſuch and ſuch, are Perſecutors of the Saints, debauched, profane &amp;c. or they are treacherous, and may endanger their Truſt to the Enemy; the Malignants have acceſſe and favour more then fitting &amp;c. with infinite beſides, the leaſt of which being ſufficient cauſe without Examination, &amp; legall tryall or proceeding Marſhall or Civill to deprive them of their Commands, if by tedious attendance full of perplexities, wants and miſeries, they have not been forced to quit them or ſtarved out of them.</p>
            <p>And wherein ſuch or like practices come ſhort of their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161687:4"/>
jealouſies and diſcontents are ſomented between the Officer in Chiefe, and ſuch as are ſubordinate unto them; eſpecially, where there they find inclinable men and ambitious ſpirits, to ſuch offers of perferment are made, as their ſuperiours commands &amp;c. apt ſuell, and very catching amongſt Souldiers, and the only alluring bait to rend and divide Officers and Souldiers. Or otherwiſe thus, <hi>viz.</hi> In favouring ſuch men (as are conceived fitteſt to bring on their Deſign) with more conſtant pay or greater allowance, whilſt the Chiefe Commander or Officer, on whoſe ſhoulders lie the greateſt charge (and who frequently have employed with their purſes and credits to furniſh the defects inſident to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands) are unjuſtly ſleighted and aſperſed.</p>
            <p>And againe, where a Brigade or other diſtinct Command have been united by ſpeciall Order for particular Services, yea, and where their duty have been one and the ſame; notwithſtanding, the one as of the Corum or greater Truſt, have been conſtantly payed; the other (although without exception inferiour to none in courage, activity, and integrity,) nothing, of purpoſe to invite or allure the Souldiers of the one to deſert them and inliſt with the other.</p>
            <p>And to this I adde another as probable, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch a Garriſon, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, &amp;c. is ſuperfluous, uſeleſſe, and ſuch Forces Supernumerary, and therefore to be ſleighted or Reduced out of hand, though with as much dexterity, a pretended ſanctified brother again repoſſeſſes that Garriſon; and the Reduced Forces by another brother of the ſame ſtamp are again inlifted, that the Kingdome may be eaſed of Supenumeraries, Reprobates as they call them, to enlarge the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their Saints.</p>
            <p>But now to another; That is to ſay, when by Order or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of <hi>Parliament,</hi> effectuall Authority hath been granted, to ſuch or ſuch to Command ſuch a Garriſon, Caſtle &amp;c. wherein much fidelity and care was performed in many ſtreights and difficulties, where not only Garriſons, but ſtrong filled Forces of the Enemy have continually been (whilſt any Enemies did appear in any part of the Kingdome:) Nevertheleſſe before both Houſes had thought expedient or fit to Demoliſh or ſleight ſuch Garriſon, Caſtle &amp;c. or Reduce ſuch Forces, a ſingle Order of the Houſe of Commons hath been by ſtrong Forces of Horſe and Foot forced upon them; yea, and often before any Order at all for that purpoſe, whole
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161687:5"/>
Regiments of Horſe and Foot have ſurrendred their Quarters, and lien upon them ſo cloſe, as at a Leaguer, when by the encroaching Enemies, they had been left ſcarce bread, and what the Enemy in their height of proſperity durſt not attempt; thoſe brethren of fraud, by a pretended friendſhip obtain, thinking thereby to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate a Disbanding, and this when the Kingdome was Reduced and wholy at their diſpoſe to Quarter where they would.</p>
            <p>And here obſerve the fraudulent uſage, theſe reduced Officers met with all; Ordinances of <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſtrong Declarations, Covenants, Promiſes of conſtant Pay, Honour, and infinite other the like plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible pretences, to raiſe or induce them to raiſe and take up Armes, are caſt before their eyes; but the danger paſt, Enemies quelled, and thoſe men triumfantly ſettled in a flouriſhing condition of eaſe and profit: A bare <hi>Mandamus</hi> from the Houſe of Commons is then thought ſufficient Authority to Disband them, without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of any thing; where to the contrary, their Modell bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren receive encouragement, are applauded and deemed men of much holineſſe, for being diſobedient and refractory<hi>:</hi> The other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for obedience, a reprobate and profane Rabble. But that it may appear, theſe men of diſobedience have been of more repute and better provided for, let the Ordinance of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 24. 1647. bear witneſſe, wherein as a frontiſ-piece or uſher of good hopes, two Ordinances of the ſame Date, ſeemingly proffer an ample proviſion for the generallity of Reduced Souldiers, out of the Exciſe, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents Eſtates, but preſently in the Rear marched a third Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the ſame Date, which not only cuts of the Reduced Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers hopes therein, but gives the ſaid Exciſe and Delinquents Eſtates, with the addition of Biſhops Lands unto their godly, as they call themſelves, though indeed the children of diſobedience, <hi>(moſt conſcientious dealing)</hi> thoſe being in ſtanding pay, the other long ſince reduced and having not wherewithall to buy their bread.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, although theſe men have neither deſerved well from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> of whom they are ill members and worſe principled, bringing diſhonour upon that Honourable Aſſembly, becauſe of their baſe ends, their Countrey for whoſe good they pretendedly ſate; or to the honeſt Souldier who deſerved better from them; yet that their qualities and not their names may appear (although both are well known unto me, and could juſtifie the verity of each particular herein Charged, have pointed at the time, when,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161687:5"/>
where, and by whom, but unwilling to act by their example, &amp; to aſperſe or lay ſo groſſe calumny upon the particular perſon of any with whom in a cauſe ſo pious we did partake, although degenerate &amp; fallen from good prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, &amp; at a moſt vaſt diſtance from us &amp; honeſty. Nevertheleſs, purpoſing rather to drive home to their conſciences their numerous errors &amp; atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call actions, and to excuſe the innocent, then accuſe any, I have therefore thought fit to add their enſuing <hi>dealings</hi> with us, which to the judicious may ſuffice to clear and vindicate the reduced Officers from that moſt unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian like aſperſion of <hi>protracting the War,</hi> ſuggeſted purpoſely to effect the deſignes now on foot; and which with much greater reaſon ſhould be charged upon the Sectaries, who unjuſtly aſſume the honour of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries Saviours as their due, and onely proper to them: Although the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting reduced ſouldiers</hi> in all Services, to the finiſhing or full compleating of the War, are known to have born the greateſt ſhare; having during three or four yeers continually, and in the ſtrength, heat, cream, and gallantry of their enemies (whileſt forreign and home Recruits of money, horſes, plate, &amp;c. came abundantly to their aid) withſtood them, and ſpun their gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, even their prime gentry &amp;c. into a deſperate, deſtitute, and dejected con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, although not without much perill and miſery on their part. And though I am not ignorant that theſe may come into ſuch hands as will joy in our diviſions, (having ſpared my pains herein a long time for that very purpoſe); yet rather then ſuffer ſo unjuſtly, and that perpetually, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likewiſe that thoſe men are not ignorant of thoſe harſh practiſes againſt us, I thought fit publickly to appear in our vindication (which indeed comes not forth without extreme neceſſity) hoping our long patience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch heavie aſperſions may juſtly excuſe us. And here 6 wayes are to be taken notice of whereby deſerving men have been injured.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The conſtant practice of detaining pay, that their ſouldiers might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert them, and repair unto others which were better paid, even thoſe very men, or like them, that are now in high eſteem; <hi>viz.</hi> Sectaries.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Shortning Relief or Recruits of horſe, arms, &amp;c. whereby the Enemy may get an advantage againſt them, that they might come to diſhonour or diſgrace; which being once got into the mouths of ſuch inſtruments as are for that purpoſe ſet on foot, thoſe honeſt ſouldiers are nipt off, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther renowned champions ſpoken of are ſtraightways ingrafted in their ſtead.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Not enabling men (of integrity, without exception) with power to puniſh for any crime, purpoſely that their Souldiers might grow licentious and unruly, thereby hoping diſhonour may come unto their Commander, and Petitions from the Country, or the parts where ſuch Commander ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to requeſt his removal, that ſo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:161687:6"/>
4 The ſending forth their renegado Tub-preachers, male and female, into every Gariſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not onely to inſtruct and teach licentiouſneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Souldiers, but to try the Commanders how they did affect that Doctrine, that where they were deſpiſed, they might not onely ſhake the duſt off their feet againſt ſuch men, but haſten into the Army to —, and with him, and others of his cut, raiſe infamous reports againſt whom they pleaſed; which muſt be ſwiftly carried about, that no authour may be catcht with it: and thus unheard, unſeen, theſe guiltleſſe ſouls are betrayed, whilſt up comes a brother, <hi>ut ſupra, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That ſouldiers ſhould more cheerfully decline their imployments, and leſs earneſtly proceed in demand of arears: the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſervice is ſeemingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, to which (being exceedingly devoted) they do with as much reality tender themſelves, and with all diligence ſpeedily endeavour to ſtrengthen their forces, ſtill ſcrewing up their credits aſwel to recruit as to keep on foot thoſe they have, when words and promiſes, their remaining remedy for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall months, are thredbare worn, and can prevail no longer, whileſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of conſequent as to the accompliſhing of ſuch propoſals comes to their relief, until the Country diſtaſting the preſſures of free quarter, riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and force them to disband, or their other neceſſities diſſipate or diſperſe them. Colonel <hi>Devereux,</hi> Colonel <hi>Mydhop,</hi> and ſundry others have ſuffered much herein: and others there are which obediently quit their commands in the model Army according to order, aſwell to ſhew their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, as to take on that ſervice, met with no better uſage herein; let Colonel <hi>Sheffield,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Pie,</hi> Quarter-maſter General <hi>Fincher,</hi> Colonel <hi>Butler</hi> and many beſides, add to this their knowledge.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To bring up the rear with the ſingle example of a ſingular deſerving man (the Van in ſpight of malice without exception) Colonel <hi>Graves</hi> is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to guard the Kings perſon: but whether doubtfull his command might become permanent or laſting, and in time by his gallantry extinguiſh thoſe new lights, he is deſigned to be ſurprized by a crew of <hi>&amp;c's.</hi> without order, and hardly eſcaped with his life: his ſouldiers, like as Col. <hi>Sheffields,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Pies,</hi> Col. <hi>Poynes,</hi> and many gallant men beſides put on and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to mutiny againſt them. To theſe I could add infinite other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples; but let theſe ſuffice at preſent.</p>
            <p>And though I have willingly paſt over many unſupportable ſufferings of thoſe Reformadoes or reduced Officers, becauſe I would haſten unto the obſtructions they met withall after reducement, untill when <hi>General Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> and the <hi>Councel of the Army</hi> ſet forth their <hi>Repreſentation to both Houſes</hi> of the 7 of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1647. in which their Saint-like charity, with the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs attendance, and future expectations of thoſe wanting Gentlemen may appear.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:161687:6"/>
And thus having been deſpitefully dealt withall by their tax-maſters, and with menaces unſupportable compeld to quit their fair though deer bought holds in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> neither furniſhed with jewel &amp;c. or other borrowd ſtuff to ſupport ſo endleſſe a journy, yea without conſideration had of their ſalary, arears, or other maintenance either for the preſent or the future, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move and march on towards the <hi>Land of promiſe</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> under the conduct of much promiſed hope where they incounter not onely with a large and deep ſea or gulf full of miſeries far unlike that the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> quietly marches over &amp; more in reſemblance to the other which met with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt in the rear) but a wilderneſſe of endleſſe ſcarcitie, (where in ſtead of better meat, they are fain to feed on fraudulent <hi>Orders,</hi> ſcornful anſwers, and lying promiſes; or, what is worſe, the <hi>pillar, cloud, light, their director,</hi> is endeavoured to be vailed from their eyes, and pillars of <hi>New light from Satan</hi> obtrude, who guide the Kingdoms treaſure and theſe mens wages into his <hi>Infernal Country,</hi> for the ſecurity of theſe his Saints the blinde guides): A wilderneſſe not improperly to ſuch as ſince this reducement have made trial of <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> and numerous removes to the ſeveral <hi>Committees</hi> of <hi>Aſſociated Counties</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> chiefly that of Accounts at <hi>Free-mans Hall, London,</hi> a Labyrinth, with the ſeveral wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and turnings whereof, never yet bottomed by any; where they are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath to accuſe themſelves, and never the neerer to effect their purpoſe; and where alſo, although they bring good Certificates for actual ſervice, from their <hi>chief Officer,</hi> ſufficient Avouchers, perfect Audits, and full and juſt Teſtimonials under the hands of <hi>Country</hi> ſtanding <hi>Committees</hi> or <hi>Sub-Committees</hi> for Accounts; (things paſt thorow and gotten with exceeding great difficulty and expence from thoſe two laſt ſorts of men eſpecially, who are continually averſe and at enmity with Souldiers; it may juſtly be ſuſpected by order or inſtruction from their Maſters:) difficult indeed, I ſay, to be attained unto by the reduced Officers; although the godly party (that ſince the Kingdoms reducement have became their Countries defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and neither before or ſince purchaſed it at ſo dear a price) have found better ſucceſſe: But, as I ſaid, where Reformadoes with much expence, and poſtings into the remoteſt Countries of the Kingdom, have at laſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected their deſires abroad, and full of hopes returned to <hi>Free-mans hall;</hi> there yet again they are retarded: either there wants an Eſtabliſhment, a full Committee, their Clerks ſervants and door-keepers are grown Maſters, and cannot be compelled to attend unleſſe they may be better paid: a juſt exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and more becoming a Souldier to have ſtood upon, when his wages was detained, and his life in hazard, then ſuch petty Clerks, and a cauſleſſe complaint too, if well examined: for it is well known, that there are Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers have ſold or pawned their clothes to purchaſe diſpatch and acceſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161687:7"/>
from thoſe Leeches: but there is yet a <hi>remora</hi> which retards their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: either it is <hi>Term-</hi>time, and the Counſellors Members of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee (without whom their Colleagues, Tradeſmen and Citizens, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and not ſo well vers'd in that calling (it ſhould ſeem) fearful to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip their knowledge, dare not proceed) muſt attend their profit at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter:</hi> or it is <hi>Exchange-time,</hi> and the vacation of the other concerns them as much: Which <hi>ſhuffle</hi> and <hi>pack</hi> really comes from <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and but in ſpecies from thoſe Gentlemen of that Committee, of whom in this I have not the leaſt thought of guilt, onely that they dare not offend—<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Which may the better be diſcovered, if obſerved how often they petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for redreſſe herein, but never received ſatisfaction, neither could they ever underſtand of any Order, Ordinance, or other Inſtructions of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their behalf, until <hi>Birch</hi> his Ordinance of the 28 of <hi>May,</hi> 1647, faſt and looſe: faſt, I ſay, as to the completing or beſting any mans Accounts complete or perfect (an ingratiating policie of a ſeeming Presbyterian, who needed no Ordinance for audit of his accounts, being well paid before, or he is extremely belyed); but looſe, and very clear, as to any thing that could intrap or beat down the Souldiers accounts: all which did give them juſt cauſe to ſuſpect that nothing leſſe was intended, then by ſuch delays they might be inforced to contract debts upon them, whereby at length they ſhould be neceſſitated to flee their demands, and quit further claim; or (as by my experience I may ſpeak it) be forced to contract with—for a ſmall part in ſatisfaction of all.</p>
            <p>And thus, whilſt they lie under the greateſt and higheſt rage that malice can inflict, ſtill chaſte and unmoveable to their Covenant, its Parliament and friends, modeſtly expreſſing their unfeigned neceſſities by Petition and other deportments of civility, they reſerve rough and ſleighting anſwers, geſtures and looks of reproach (fit objects for ſcorn and revenge in high ſpirits, and may not unjuſtly be ſuſpected intendedly to have been put upon them to enforce mutiny, or ſome act properly fit or apt for Queſtion, and loſſe of their <hi>Arrears:</hi> witneſſe the black liſt, and other menaces many, bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears that frequently ſtand aloft to affright <hi>Reformadoes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that theſe great profeſſors of <hi>Zeale</hi> (full as impious in their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as blaſted in their piety) could ſtrain at a gnat and ſwallow a Cammel full glib, let the Records, Orders and Ordinances of their <hi>Derby-houſe</hi> and—&amp;c. beare record with their unſanctified conſciences and come in Judgement againſt them: what vaſt gratuities of thouſands have been dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over &amp; toſt from one member to another &amp; joyntly (none diſſenting) to their godly deſerving brethren, in recompence of pretended (though falſe) loſſes, and as many (falſely uſurped) ſervices, performed by more deſerving men, and by <hi>Peters</hi> the Poſt ſnatcht from them and preſented to the—you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161687:7"/>
may imagine in another ſhape: ſome of which members had never been worth the 20 part of the gratuities given them, and others whoſe eſtates were vaſte, full as great in avarice, without remorſe of Conſcience or thankfulneſſe to God, or thoſe wanting ſouldiers (that as a ſcrine ſtood between the enemie and them, their lives and eſtates) hurd up their wages, and the Kingdoms treaſurs, that rather ſhould (out of their own plentifull eſtates preſented to their hands) have contributed to the releife of their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities. And here likewiſe the ungratefulneſſe of many Divines is not to be paſt over, that in an audience proper, at ſeaſons fit and apt, upon texts of Scripture, rather complain of Leane Benifices, promote themſelves and their intereſt, boaſt what miraculous victories their prayers have wrought, how they ſtood in the gap, and what God hath done for them in this worke, in every pulpit inforcing their own praiſe, and artributing to the ſouldiers nothing, (where they might have told him to be contented with his wages when he can catch it:) It is undeniable that the prayers of many godly men prevailed much, to which the courage ſtrength activity or force of the Souldiers, (I mean chiefly the firſt undertakers) was not compatible: <hi>for a Horſe is a vain help, and ſhall not deliver any by his great ſtrength:</hi> (nevertheleſſe herein are not ſuch praiſe worthy inſtruments (that couragiouſly indeavoured to perform their obligation to God and their Country) to be forgotten.</p>
            <p>Now when as much time had been ſpent in expectations, and many lean faces did expreſſe the wants they met withall at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed ſuch objects of pittie came ſo frequent into open view, or of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to decoy them into the Country, amongſt their friends and kindred for recrute of fleſh and cloths) the deluding Ordinance of the tenth of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 1646, is prepared, which directs them for pay to the Countries or aſſocaitions in which they had formerly ſerved, where thoſe perfidious Committees in obedience to the private inſtructions of their Maſters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, are prepared with delayes for all, but pay to none, and at the laſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter much chargeable time ſpent and more experience gained to no purpoſe, they return to <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> where objected to grow numerous, new plots are ſooner projected then diſcovered, the houſes are in danger, and thoſe <hi>quondam</hi> friends the Reformadoes muſt now be reputed new ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or to judge more charitably, (the houſes being carefull of their ſafetie in a time of inraged ſickneſſe (that had rather by much open their treaſures to bury a ſtarved ſoule of them, then to preſerve him alive) they muſt not indanger their perſons within 20 miles of <hi>London,</hi> unto whom the Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts are thought fit to be coupled, whoſe penalty extends only to impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but to the other <hi>(viz)</hi> their old friends the <hi>Reformadoes</hi> they add be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides impriſonment the forſeit of their arrears, whereas had they in anſwer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161687:8"/>
to any of their modeſt petitions or humble requeſts receiv'd but any aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that they ſhould have been payed or provided for, moſt of them had of their free accord quit the City and their chargeable attendance at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I though improper to my tax, yet being proper to this ſubject, I cou'd have ſpoken on an object of far greater pietie, <hi>(viz</hi> Gentlemen and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that have lived in good repute in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which here have neither friends to recrute fleſh or cloths with, or houſes that they can confidently put their heades into &amp; alſo forced to wander in the ſame progreſſe at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall</hi> out of their zeal &amp; affection to the truth, (which you ſeemingly profeſſe) that nevertheleſſe dayly paſſe by their wounded brethren full of anguiſh as the Prieſt and Levit did, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. when with Charity and juſtice, they ſhould have been imployed into their country againſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God and their Peace before any: And had I not undertaken to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal names, ſuch high crimes happily had forced me here to have culled out certaine of their unworthy country men, men in power and full of envy that comply with any for profit though to the ruine of their country and theſe poore ſoules; but this ſubject requires a volume, and therefore I am forced to ſhorten it here with this digreſſion. Only let me ſay, thus much; I finde in Fames record <hi>Mr. Aneſly</hi> and Sir <hi>William Perſons</hi> honeſt true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted men and beſide them few.</p>
            <p>Forasmuch therefore as their afflictions have been untolerable in the eyes of juſt men (unto whom only they appeal and before whom they ſhall alwayes endeavour to approve themſelves candid in their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and contienſcious to their undertakings) they cannot conceive wherefore any juſt guilt ſhould ſtick upon them, being unchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably the ſame, alwayes as willing and ready as ever they have been, with their blood and lives to ſtand up in defence of their Covenant and in it, their <hi>Religiion &amp;c: their King &amp;c: the Parliament of England &amp;c: the Subjects &amp;c.</hi> and all the <hi>Covenants Legitimate</hi> brethren, defenders thereof againſt violence and oppreſſion: unleſſe it be a crime to acknowledge this, as many reduced officers by their petitions did the laſt of <hi>Iune,</hi> unto the Parliement then full and under no force, And within a little after, with their City bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren at Saint <hi>Iames-Fields, Guild-Hall,</hi> and other places (from whom they expected a fuller meaſure of love and fixed performance for their kindneſſe; But I wiſh in my heart they may not repent it, or gratfully remember it when God ſhall pleaſe to viſite them with better times:) by an order of both Houſes ſhould have manifeſted (and beleeve it) ſhall again <hi>Nemine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra dicenti</hi> whenſoever that cauſe and the like authority ſhall require them: If I ſay this be a crime wherefore was It Impoſed, and being impoſed we and not you are the Judges of our own <hi>Conſciences,</hi> you might have made
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161687:8"/>
Interpretation of it to your ends, and our ſatisfaction in eaſe of conſcience before it came to be impoſed; but by your leave being taken, your ſopheſtry may not excuſe us before God, he beareth record with our conſciences in what ſence we received it; which accordingly by the Almighty help with life and limbe we will maintain. To impoſe it (if a crime) was yours, and the breach thereof ſhall never be laid to our charge God willing but how that may, be exacted from you, after this life, may be ſuppoſed; but becauſe that may be leaſt feared I wave it; however I dare confidently tell you there is in this life a day of account like to come and that ſpeedily, where that pack-horſe for carrying on deſignes, even that very ſleighted thing will In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force their humble ſubmiſſion, even theirs that ſo much ſcorned and derided it, where the abuſe of Religion, King, Kingdom, and its vaſte treaſures for ſelfe ends, will come in judgement againſt them; in the mean time it behoveth your <hi>Committees, Exciſe men, Sequeſtrators,</hi> and vaſaliſed Rable &amp;c. to preſſe hard for an act of <hi>Indemnity,</hi> and it will as much concern you at that day to make ſtrong proviſion for them as for your ſelves, for through them your nakedneſſe will appear, and your galled ſides will ſore trouble you. I ſay no more, a few words to the wiſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Pray are not thoſe reduced officers oblig'd to defend the Parliaments rights and priviledges? what then is the jealouſie? do they not know for whom they acted, how dangerous and fatal it may prove unto them if they ſhould advance any other intereſt? where then lies the diſtruſt? Is not their pay and arrears the fruits of their hard ſervice utterly loſt if they ſhould relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh the Parliament of <hi>England?</hi> what then on their part can be feared? O myſterie, how is this riddle to be unfolded? mary I conceive by the ſaid Repreſentation of Generall <hi>Fairfax</hi> and his councel of the Army, and a gratifying Ordinance from the Parliament formerly expreſſed which tells you of no other arreras or admittance to any audit for arrears but his army and ſuch as did adhere to them, when they marched up—you know when, where and how, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how? adhere to that army with whom they had no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parl. to joyn? the army by order of Parliament, molded to a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber certain in officers &amp; ſouldiers, and then compleat (if not exceeding their number) in both? that army which contrary to its orders from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment refuſed to disband, marched up beyond its bonds; forſt, awed, and gave orders to <hi>&amp;c.—</hi>their Maſters? An Army that abhor the covenant and ſuch as adhere unto it; diſoblige government and all of its tenent? An Army that priſe none but ſectaries and libertines who onely are advanced by it and none but they from ſuch good Lord, deliver my Reformado friends Say, what have thoſe reduced officers or ſouldiers gotten, that were not of you, but for a time and neceſſity marcht with you? What preferment, what arrears, what expected ſatisfaction? were they not preſently after
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161687:9"/>
excepted againſt and disbanded as ſupernumeraries, went off without their pay which others had? With ſuch comrades and of ſuch principles, I am confident the reduced Officers will be exceeding cautious hereafter to joyn.</p>
            <p>But as to thoſe that have been of a long time reduced from other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, recruted or ignorant at firſt of the deſignes, did inſiſt in the Modell army (which are at this day the better part of their Armies horſe and foot) old Souldiers who had been marſhilled, exerciſed and drawn forth, under the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and other faithful Commanders of the Covenant ſtamp, of which ſort I ſay at this day is the better part of the Army <hi>(other Officers excepted)</hi> to whom as they are honeſt men and of the firſt principles, from my heart I wiſh increaſe of happineſſe and honour (things never to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto in that Army) and now as their reall friend let me adviſe them to be both vigilant and very circumſpect how to take for currant ſuch droſſe as their mechanick Officers would force upon them or through their ſtrength and power, build ſuch ſtrong fabricks for their Officers great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe upon the deſtruction of Covenant, King and Kingdome: be wiſe in time my friends, come out of her, leſt you ſhare in her plagues: It is gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally known that the cup of her filthineſſe fornication <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is brimfull: there fore return in time to your firſt principles.</p>
            <p>And in concluſion I ſhall requeſt that the plainneſſe or naked truths of my expreſſions may be excuſed in two reſpects, and not at all imputed to concern a third. Firſt for the anguiſh of our preſent ſufferings; which was hoped that no heart ſo adamant in tyranie but would have relented, or relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ere this, our wants: the other being the continuance without intermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of that ſpirit of inveterat ſplene &amp; malice with which we were redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, (remorſ in neither appearing though long &amp; untill this preſent which with much patience and conſtancy expected,) forced theſe deſperate truths with as much modeſty as could be is performed, (our ſufferings balanced) but if any part therein may ſeemingly reflect upon <hi>the Parliament of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or its friends (for when we were by Covenant bound to fight and, pray,) and ſhall accordingly God aſſiſting) being that meant in the third place let it be clear from my purpoſe or theirs for whom this is underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and put upon the ſcore of ſuch degenerte brats who deſigne and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe what to the utmoſt extent of their power may to overthrow Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, King, Covenant and Kingdome: Ingeniouſly thoſe are the men meant and no other, over whom in ballance of that black liſt prepared for us here a Scottiſh black liſt or miſt ſtands touring for them and their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from whoſe plots, practiſes and deſignes</p>
            <closer>Great Samaritane preſerve us.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
